Finding Aid for the Leonidas Chalmers Glenn Papers
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
Leonidas Chalmers Glenn
multiple
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0171
8.75 linear_feet
Biographical Sketch
September 8, 1871 Born near King’s Mountain, North Carolina; son of William D. and Sarah P. Glenn; boyhood spent in Crowders Creek valley, North Carolina
1891 Bachelors degree, University of South Carolina
1891-1896 Teacher i n South Carolina Public Schools
1894-1896 Superintendent o f schools, Darlington, South Carolina
Summer, 1896 Attended Harvard University (studied under William Morris Davis)
1896-1899 Doctorate work at Johns Hopkins University; Ph.D. awarded, 1899
1899-1900 Adjunct professor geology and biology, University of South Carolina
September 12, 1900 Married Nellie Louise McCullough, of Darlington, S.C.
Fall, 1900 Became adjunct professor of geology, Vanderbilt University
1903 Became full professor and chairman of Department of Geology, Vanderbilt
1928 Became head of Science Division, Vanderbilt
1942 Retired as Emeritus Professor of Geology, Vanderbilt
1900-1908 Assistant geologist with United State Geological Survey
1916-1917 On leave to work with Sinclair Oil Company
1918 Acting state geologist, Tennessee
1918-1919 Special agent in oil and gas valuation, Department of Internal Revenue
1919 Geological expert i n Red River boundary dispute between Oklahoma and Texas, Department of Justice
1935-1951 Member of Board of Consultants, Tennessee Valley Authority Consultant, United States Army Corps of Engineers
January 11, 1951 Died, Nashville.
- TVA Dams
  - Chatuge, (1941) (Box 1)
  - Cherokee, (1940-1941) (Box 1)
    geology, embankment design, soil laboratory report, rock forms, construction progress, photographs, consultants visi ts
  - Chickamauga, (1935-1940) (Box 1)
    watertable profiles, geologic elements, soil foundation, embankment, progress reports on construction, resistivit y measurements, cost data, ground water investigations
  - Coulter Shoals, (1936-1939) (Box 1)
    geologic report, constultants report, rock surface conditions
  - Douglas, (1942) (Box 1)
    construction progress
  - Fontana, (1942-1944) (Box 1)
    information for consultants
- TVA Dams
  - Fort Loudoun, (1940-1942) (Box 2)
    preliminary investigation, embankment design, soil reports, consultants report
  - Gilbertsville, (1937-1944) (Box 2)
    effecton area economy, photographs, progress report, consulting engineers reports, cost estimates, blueprints
  - Guntersville, (1936-1939) (Box 2)
    Honeycomb Cave, consulting engineers reports, groundwater conditions
  - Hiwassee, (1936-1942) (Box 2)
    earthquakes in Tennessee Valley, photographs, geologic sections, report of consulting engineers, geologic drawings
  - South Holston, (1942) (Box 2)
    consulting engineers memorandum
  - Kentucky, (1939-1943) (Box 2)
    consulting engineers reports, soiltesting and embankment design, Kentucky project statistics, progress reports.
  - Lower Tennessee, (1935-1936) (Box 2)
    preliminary report
- TVA Dams
  - Norris, (1935) (Box 3)
    summary of principal features
  - Nottely, (1941) (Box 3)
  - Pickwick Landing, (1935-1939) (Box 3)
    summary of principal features, report on construction
  - Vasper Water Table, (1939) (Box 3)
  - Watauga, (1947) (Box 3)
  - Watts Bar, (1938-1940) (Box 3)
    report of consultants, geology of dam site, soiltests, reports on construction program, photographs
  - Wheeler, (1935-1939) (Box 3)
    summary of principal features, photographs, report of consulting engineers
  - Wilson, (1935-1939) (Box 3)
  - Wolf Creek, (1940) (Box 3)
    definite project report, data for consultants
  - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
    "The Tennessee Valley Experiment" (reprint from Engineering News-Record, December, 1936)
    Travel regulations for consultants, 1935
    Pamphlets and press releases on the TVA by Harcourt A. Morgan (1935 and 1936) and David E. Lilienthal (1936)
    Symposium on Masonry Dams
    "Geology of the Dam Sites of the Tennessee Valley Region"
    Bibliography on Dams for 1924-1938 compiled by the Engineer School, Fort Belvoir, Virginia
    Information on a l l dams for consultant inspection trips:February, May, July, September, 1941
- Dams Other Than TVA
  - Table Rock (Arkansas and Missouri), 1942-1945 (Box 4)
  - Water Valley (Arkansas and Missouri), 1940-1941 (Box 4)
  - Conchas (New Mexico), 1939 (Box 4)
  - Falmouth (Kentucky), 1942 (Box 4)
  - Fort Peck (Montana), 1938 (Box 4)
  - Fort Supply (Arkansas), 1938 (Box 4)
  - Greer’s Ferry (Arkansas), 1940 (Box 4)
  - John Martin (Colorado), 1940-1942 (Box 4)
  - Lone Rock (Arkansas), 1941 (Box 4)
  - Nuuanu (Hawaii), 1932 (Box 4)
  - Flood Control (Box 4)
  - World Power and High Dams (Box 4)
  - International Union of Geodsey and Geophysics, 1939 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous information of water power projects (Box 4)
- Dams Other Than TVA
  - Caddoa (Colorado), 1940-1941 (Box 5)
  - Chamita, Jemez, Chiflo (Arizona), 1945-1946 (Box 5)
- Arkansas Oil/Thompson & Co. (Earthquake, Reelfoot Lake, 1926) (Box 6)
- Charts of Various Activities of the State Forestry Commission, Ala. & Ga., 1936 (Box 6)
- Consulting Reports for TVA, 1904-1941 (Box 6)
- Dam Site Geology (Visit of L. C. Glenn), Dec, 29, 1939 (Box 6)
- Dataon Coal Land, Pulaski-, Va., Dec. 1923 (Box 6)
- Earthquake Forces on Dams, June 18, 1931 (Box 6)
- Forest Resources of the Norris Dam Watershed, 1936 (Box 6)
- Geological Maps of Western Kentucky Coal Fields (Box 6)
- Georgia State Museum, 1936 (Box 6)
- Glenn’s School Notes, Johns Hopkin University (Box 6)
- Great Sraokie Mountains Literature (Box 6)
- Group Photo, Kentucky Dam (Box 6)
- Kentucky State Parks, Annual, 1935 (Box 6)
- List of Patents (Box 6)
- Literature on New Hampshire and Weeks Law, Silver Jubilee Maps: (Box 6)
  - Henry County, Tennessee, 1922
  - Chester County, Tennessee, 1918
  - Carroll County, Tennessee, 1926
  - Hardeman County, Tennessee, 1923
  - Henderson County, Tennessee
  - Black and St. Francis River Commission of Missouri, 1927
  - Subdistrict No. 3 of Grassy Lake and Tyronza DD. No. 9
  - Mississippi County, Arkansas
  - General Contours
  - Subdistrict No. 1 (Carson Lake D.D. No. 8) Mississippi County
  - Arkansas Contour Map
  - Tennessee Valley and Adjacent territories
- Meterology Notes (Box 6)
- Miscellaneous Photographs (Box 6)
- Notes on Earthquakes, Dams and Salt Deposits (Box 6)
- Notes, 1929 (Box 6)
- Patent, 1883 (Box 6)
- Suit (Box 6)
- TVA---Earthquakes and other reports (Box 6)
- TVA---Red Iron Ores (Neal Suit) (Box 6)
- Virginia Forest Service (Box 6)
- L.C. Glenn Papers, updated December 31, 2014 (Box 6)
- TVA, 1942 (Box 7)
- Info of Interest (Box 7)
- Progress Items (Box 7)
- Progress Reports (Box 7)
- TVA Lawsuits (Box 7)
- Bell Foley (Box 7)
- Caddoa (Box 7)